### Nicholas J. Wilson

[version date 2024.05]

nj.wilson@outlook.com
linkedin.com/in/njwsn/

#### **PROFILE**

Economist and development researcher interested in understanding fragility. I field surveys and use geospatial data to study attitudes, beliefs, programs, policy, and political economy in East Africa. Formerly based in China, Germany, Kenya, the Netherlands, Russia, UK; now South Sudan/Turkey.

#### **EDUCATION**

#### Ludwig-Maximilians-Universität München

Munich, DE

2020-23

Economics, MSc Grade: 1.14, Sehr Gut (Top ranked student)

• Visiting student: Higher School of Economics - Moscow.

**University of Warwick** 

Coventry, GB

Economics, BSc (Hons) Grade: 70, First Class 2013-17

· Visiting student: University of Amsterdam.

#### **EXPERIENCE**

**Forcier Consulting** 

Juba, SS/Istanbul, TR

Research Manager 2022-Present

- Manage an office of 18 staff conducting mixed methods research across South Sudan.
- Field surveys, focus groups, and interview programs, and analyze geospatial data and policies.
- Negotiate with clients, train researchers, supervise field data collection, manage project budgets.
- Advise on political economy and logistics of program implementation in the country and region.

#### University of Massachusetts (UMass) Amherst

Remote

Research Assistant

2021-22

- Research Assistant (RA) for Prof. Lucy Xiaolu Wang, conducting research in health economics.
- Activities included literature reviews, data cleaning and analysis, managed several junior RAs.

#### **Max Planck Institute for Innovation and Competition**

Munich, DE

Research Assistant

2020-21

- RA for Prof. Lucy Xiaolu Wang, conducting research in health and innovation economics.
- Activities included literature reviews, data cleaning and analysis, management of a junior RA.

#### **United Nations Development Programme (UNDP)**

Nairobi, KE

Communications Consultant

2019-20

- Served as comms & partnerships focal point for UNDP's Governance & Inclusive Growth portfolio.
- Conducted fieldwork and participated in M&E missions to more than 20 counties across Kenya.

#### **OC&C Strategy Consultants**

London, GB

Associate Consultant

2018-19

- Strategy, market research, and commercial due diligence consulting projects for clients in EMEA.
- Built market forecasts, visualized spatial data, analyzed surveys, interviewed industry players.

Magic Panda International 能猫国际集团	Shanghai, CN
International E-Commerce Intern	Winter 2017

Rothschild & Co

London, GB

Investment Banking Summer Intern

Summer 2016

Lazard London, GB
Investment Banking Summer Intern Summer 2015

#### **SELECTED CONSULTANCIES**

#### Maternal and Child Health Baseline Study in Aweil East (2024)

Contracted by the International Rescue Committee (IRC) to design a methodology for and undertake a quantitative survey of maternal health and newborn care indicators in Aweil East, South Sudan.

## Scoping Study on Agriculture and Food Security Value Chains in South Sudan (2024) Contracted by Norweigan Church Aid (NCA) to undertake a qualitative analysis of the landscape, challenges, and opportunities for agriculture value chain addition in 5 states of South Sudan.

# Education Research in Conflict and Protracted Crises (ERICC) in South Sudan (2023-24) Contracted by IRC to synthesize education in emergencies research priorities for South Sudan through a literature review, key informant interviews, and stakeholder engagement workshops.

#### Third-Party Monitoring of South Sudan 2022/23 LLIN Distribution Campaign (2023)

Contracted by the Against Malaria Foundation (AMF) to monitor planning, distribution, and verification activities for a national campaign to distribute 5.4m mosquito nets in 7 states of South Sudan.

#### **CRC South Sudan: Healthy Bodies, Healthy Minds Qualitative Evaluation** (2022)

Contracted by the Canadian Red Cross (CRC) to conduct a project evaluation, comprising focus group discussions (FGDs) and draw, write, and tell (DWT) workshops in Warrap, South Sudan.

### Implementation of the UNHCR Forced Displaced Survey (FDS) in South Sudan (2022-23) Contracted by UNHCR to implement a major global survey initiative in South Sudan assessing living

conditions of IDPs, refugees, asylum seekers and returnees in camps and host communities.

#### **UNICEF ESARO Disability Baseline Study** (2022)

Contracted by UNICEF to produce country reports and policy briefs on barriers facing children living with disabilities and their associated programmatic needs in 8 sub-Saharan African countries.

#### **UNDP Support to Devolved Governance in Kenya: Transformational Stories** (2020)

Contracted by UNDP to contribute analyses and edit a narrative review of their support to implementation of the devolution process across Kenya, which included conducting fieldwork in 6 counties.

#### **PUBLICATIONS**

#### U.S. State Approaches to Cannabis Licensing (with Lucy Xiaolu Wang) [2022]

International Journal of Drug Policy (IJDP), 106, 103755 [IJDP]; MPI Research Paper [SSRN] Analysis of different state-level licensing and taxation policies for the US legal cannabis market.

#### **WORKS IN PROGRESS**

ERICC: An Evidence-driven Education in Emergencies Research Agenda for South Sudan (with Ioanna Wagner-Tsoni, Ceaser Taban, and Maartje Schots)

Synthesis and description of education in emergencies research priorities for South Sudan.

Challenges and Opportunities for Education in Emergencies: Voices from South Sudan (with Ioanna Wagner-Tsoni, Ceaser Taban, and Maartje Schots)

Qualitative analysis of key informant interviews from education stakeholders across South Sudan.

Conflict's Long Shadow: Evidence on Education in Emergencies in South Sudan (with Ioanna Wagner-Tsoni, Ceaser Taban, and Maartje Schots)

Systematic literature review identifying education in emergencies evidence gaps in South Sudan.

#### Hate Thy Neighbor? Conflict, Fear, and Mistrust in Kenya's White Highlands

Empirical study of long-run effects of exposure to clientelist land reforms on social discord in Kenya.

#### AWARDS, FUNDING, AND SCHOLARSHIPS

International Rescue Committee (IRC): Funding to attend CIES 2024 conference	2024
LMU Economics Alumni Club (VAC): Alumni Prize for Young Economists	2023
German Academic Exchange Service (DAAD): Scholarship for Master Studies	2020-22
Erasmus+: Study Abroad Grant	2015-16

#### **CONFERENCE PRESENTATIONS**

**2024:** Comparative and International Education Society (CIES) Conference, University of Edinburgh Centre of African Studies (CAS) and Centre for Security Research (CeSaR) Conference; African Studies Association of the UK (ASAUK) Bienniel Conference.

#### **SKILLS**

**Data analysis and visualization:** Excel, LATEX, NVivo, QGIS, Python, R, Stata, Tableau. **Field research:** M&E/QA strategy, ODK scripting, reporting, sample and survey tool design. **Project management:** coordinate research teams, design budgets & fieldwork, manage clients. **Foreign languages:** French (Intermediate), German (Intermediate), Turkish (Intermediate).

#### **PERSONAL**

Citizenship: dual citizen of Ireland and the UK (London is home).

#### References available on request